<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Inquiries into the causes of our miseries, whence they issue-forth upon us: and reasons wherefore they have born us down so low; and are like to carrie us yet lower. The Independents and the way of worship, they stand-up for, is renderd clear of this grievous charge... This charge is drawn-up against the Independents, by three worthies, men, I think, of name, all (I) D.P.P.W. Pryn Esquire; but more fully and with more devouring words, if more can be, by Dr. A. Steuart in his last book... In six sections. Whereof the first onely is here; a just vindication of the way of worship very commonly misunderstood; very falsly interpreted; but very truly called Independent... By Hez. Woodward.</title>
            <title>Inquiries, into the causes of our miseries. Part 1.</title>
            <author>Woodward, Ezekias, 1590-1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96893</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3491</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E22_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21697</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871480</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871480</idno>
            <idno type="VID">123891</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96893)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 123891)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 4:E22[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Inquiries into the causes of our miseries, whence they issue-forth upon us: and reasons wherefore they have born us down so low; and are like to carrie us yet lower. The Independents and the way of worship, they stand-up for, is renderd clear of this grievous charge... This charge is drawn-up against the Independents, by three worthies, men, I think, of name, all (I) D.P.P.W. Pryn Esquire; but more fully and with more devouring words, if more can be, by Dr. A. Steuart in his last book... In six sections. Whereof the first onely is here; a just vindication of the way of worship very commonly misunderstood; very falsly interpreted; but very truly called Independent... By Hez. Woodward.</title>
                  <title>Inquiries, into the causes of our miseries. Part 1.</title>
                  <author>Woodward, Ezekias, 1590-1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.]Warranted by the God of Heaven, being ordered according to His churches book on earth; and published for His churches sake in the very close of this year,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Of the six projected parts, only parts 1 and 3 were published, the latter in 1645.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decem: 23".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:123891:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:123891:1"/>
            <p>INQVIRIES Into the cauſes of our miſeries, whence they iſſue-forth upon us: And reaſons wherefore they have born us down ſo low; And are like to carrie us yet lower.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Independents</hi> and the way of worſhip, they ſtand-up for, is renderd clear of this grievous charge, That they hold forth the <hi>licentiouſneſſe of wicked conſciences; Tolerations of all ſorts of moſt deteſtable Schiſmes, Hereſies, and Religions, as Idolatries Paganiſme, Turſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſme, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deiſme, &amp;c. ſo opening a floodgate to let in this inundation of ſins, and ſorrows upon the Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This charge is drawn-up againſt the Independents, by three wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies, men, I think, of name, all (1) <hi>D. P. P. P. Pryn</hi> Eſquire; But more fully and with more devouring words, if more can be, by Dr. <hi>A. Steuart</hi> in his laſt book, which, in reference to the Brethren, thouſands in Iſrael, reliſheth as does the Gall of Aſpes, or Adders poyſon under the tongue.</p>
            <p>In ſix Sections. Whereof the firſt onely is here; A Juſt vindication of the <hi>way of worſhip</hi> very commonly miſunderſtood; very falſly inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted; but very truly called <hi>Independent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moſt humbly devoted to the Honour of Almighty God; and King of Saints; preſented to all the three Aſſemblies in all the three Kingdoms, in Parliament now, with hearts engaged upon the great matters of the Kingdom: but before and above all, to beat out a way of worſhip, holding forth to the world, a ſutableneſſe to the Great God, full-up to His Mind and Rule in His Scriptures: humbly preſented to all theſe, and to all Chriſtian people whoſe habitation is on earth, and converſation in Heaven.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Hez. Woodward.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Prov. 25. 18.</bibl> 
                  <hi>A man that beareth falſe witneſſe againſt his neighbour, is a ma<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>le and a ſword, and a ſharp arrow.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Job 42. 7.</bibl> 
                  <hi>My wrath is kindled againſt thee, and thy two friends, for ye have not ſpoken of Me the thing that was right.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Iſa. 2. 23.</bibl> 
                  <hi>Wo unto them that take away the Righteouſneſſe of the Righteous from him.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Warranted by the God of Heaven, being ordered according to His Churches book on earth; and publiſhed for His Churches ſake in the very cloſe of this year 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:123891:2"/>
            <p>Section I. <hi>VVHere the Reader is ſatisfied in point of Licencing books, Informed in the meaning of thoſe words Dependent Independent: And the men ſo called, are cleared from the cavils of the froward; Miſtakes of the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant; heavy charges of knowing men; with other grace matters worthy all mens ſad and ſerious conſiderations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Section II. <hi>Some</hi> praecognita <hi>matters already known, and granted are premiſed; As that the</hi> evils <hi>of Sin and Puniſhment are from our ſelver; Puniſhments are</hi> merae, <hi>mearly ſo where Gods Hand is immediate, and Man paſſive; or</hi> mixtae, <hi>where Gods Hand is and mans alſo; what God dies, and Man does, Gods Hand has the preheminence; Gods End and Mans</hi> Ends, <hi>how differents Gods End the Glory of His excellent Goodneſſe, His Churches Glory alſe, Some things granted in point of Reformation, how active the Divell with his ſervants are in Reforming times, and have been alwayes, as at this day, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Section III. <hi>Enquiries touching Peace, what it is; how we improve the Peace we have. Who they be that petition for Peace, and of whom; whether not of thoſe who world, but cannot give it: And of thoſe, who if they could,</hi> will <hi>not give it while the world ſtands, being adverſaries and enemies to their own peace; to the peace of God and good men; and true Religion of God, the worſhipping of Him in ſpirit and truth. All this declared and confirmed by two moſt notable ſtories out of the Chronicles of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Section IIII. <hi>Concluſions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uching war, that it is an evill, an</hi> onely <hi>evill; that our war is no more unnaturall, than it is for fire to burn; nor a civill war, as when a Kingdome fights againſt it ſelf; but ſacred, when the kingdome of darkneſſe fights againſt the kingdome of light, as now it is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Enquiries touching the Battels of the Lord, what they are; who fight theſe Battels; and what Souldiers they ought to be; how furniſhed; What hinders victory; what brings it as upon Eagles wings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Section V. <hi>Enquiries touching our keeping Covenant, and Faſting dayes; what we do, and what our Miniſters ſhould do before us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Section VI. <hi>Enquiries touching our evill Doctrines, and what may be the cauſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and whether the remedies uſed for the removing theſe</hi> Cauſes <hi>are ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, having the ſtamp of God upon them, and warrant from His mouth.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:123891:2"/>
            <head>Section 1.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader, now that you have taken-up the book, Ile do my beſt, to cloſe with thee at the firſt, as one, not a little am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious of thy favour: and therefore can be content to crave thine eye and eare both, thy beſt attention all along. Do not fear to afford me this favour; I crave it for Gods ſake; for His Cauſes ſake; for His ſervants ſake; for your ſake; the Lord knows, and not mine own; Doubting not to ſpeak all along, like a free man, and a true Subject; and not as one abuſing my li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty or my glory: But uſing it as a ſubject of the Lord Chriſt, to His glory, and the good of my Brother: Therefore I cannot doubt neither, That my words, I ſhall ſpeak, can need an Apology: And yet, that my words may have a good reliſh upon your pallate, and a ſweeter touch upon your eare, I will preface a little touching ſome matters firſt.</p>
            <p>1 Touching my licence here, I have no <hi>Imprimatur,</hi> no licence to ſpeak. To which I could anſwer, Yes, that I have, for by the grace of God, <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> the old Licenſers of old, have licenced my words all along. And truly my ſpirit could never go forth with any other way of licenſing, or <hi>midwifring</hi> ſuch births as are books into the world; ſurely no better hand to officiate there, than what <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> affords me. And if ſo be our Conceptions and Births want either one or both, let the parent ſmart for his <hi>lye;</hi> and be faſt locked in Bedlom till he recover his wits again: And if he be <hi>Libellous,</hi> as too many are, let his own place the pillory inſtruct him to better manners. But if he hasblaſphemed <hi>God,</hi> or the <hi>King of Saints,</hi> lot him find neither friend nor enemy, but let him dye, if he has blaſphemed his God. Gods Law this, and mans Law that, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried all along through a ſeries of time, and never interrupted, nor reverſed, or made null till it came thorough the Inquiſition Court at Rome, whence we have our <hi>Imprimatur,</hi> Let this be printed. And then ſure enough it ſerved to promote the Doctrines, and practiſes of the Church there, which my ſoul abominates. It will be ſaid here, That I go a croſſe-way to an Ordinance of Parliament. Truly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:123891:3"/> that ſtartles me not a little; the Lord knows, I look upon an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Parliament as an Ordinance of God, not to be diſputed, but obeyed. I kiſſe the hand of Authoritie, and am readie to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led forth <hi>to its foot</hi> therefrom to be made Active or Paſſive: yet I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conceive, that I have gone a croſſe-way to that Ordinance for licenfing-books. I went, in obedience thereunto, craving a licence, though I think it my due, and ought to be given me: but could not obtain it. The truth is, If the Book bear <hi>Independent</hi> upon its <hi>front,</hi> and be thought to ſpeak for that way (which God Himſelf will cleer and juſtifie before all the world) it is ſilenced before it ſpeaks. And ſo is dealt more injuriouſly with, than have been the greateſt offenders in the world: for they have had leave to ſpeak for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in all ages of the world upwards to <hi>as it is at this day.</hi> It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, That writing for this way of Church Government does but hinder our courſe in the way of Reformation, making the Diviſions greater, and the Rent wider. I anſwer; If I were perſwaded ſo, I would rather put my hand in fire then unto paper. But I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded in my heart clean otherwiſe, and by the grace of God ſhall be able to make it appear in the ſequell all along. It is ſaid agen: Theſe are my thoughts; that this ſcrible will do no hurt, will not make the rent wider; my Judgement onely. I anſwer, not mine one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; I have asked adviſe about it, enquired ſeriouſly into the matter, and why ſhould I be aſhamed to ſay more: I have given up my judgement unto the Lord, and I have this anſwer from him, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance from his right hand, ſo guiding mine, That I ſhall, ſo I hope, and am confident, ſpeak nothing which ſhall diſhonour his holy, holy, holy, name; nor his cauſe, nor his people, the congregations of God. I have a ſober confidence, that I have licence from Gods hand, and ſhall keep cloſe to the word of his mouth, and therefore ſith I could not have a licence from man, I can be careleſſe of it.</p>
            <p>That it may not be ſaid, I am aſhamed of my name, for indeed I am not, being it was a very good mans name (which yet I know cannot make the man the better) I have, for commanding reaſons affixed my name; though very unwilling to appear ſo openly, as I was moſt willing to do with a Licenced. But the want of it can be no ſhame to me: ſome little blame rather to him, who would not give it me; having no time to enquire into the papers, as ſome (too ſuperſtitiouſly perhaps, but their ſuperſtition teacheth) were wont to do, to enquire into a paper, which lay as low as their foot, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they would put their foot upon it with neglect; leſt the name of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:123891:3"/> their God, or ſomething of God ſhould be there. Certainly the Name of God is here; and I will not doubt to ſay again, I have His Licence to print it.</p>
            <p>But the great ſtop was becauſe this anſwering is like to cauſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer upon anſwer. I anſwer. God knows that, and will turn all to good. I am a free man, and may take my liberty, not ſtanding charged as ſervants do, not to <hi>anſwer again.</hi> And indeed <hi>I</hi> cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive what they can anſwer, unleſſe, as ſome did, who had ſpoke <q>roughly enough, and being modeſtly reproved for being ſo rough, anſwered, as roughly; that, ſith their hand was in, they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to put it forth again as roughly as ever.</q> As pleaſeth men let it be; but if I am honoured with any anſwer from a Doctor (for the other, that learned and excellent man, I hope his apprehenſions are more digeſted now, and he has repented of them, that they were indeed ſubitan, but for) the Doctor, I hope he will learn at length to reprove his Brother modeſtly and meekly, and then I ſhall accept his reproof with all thankfulneſſe; but if any roughneſſe appear as it hath to others, which I muſt rather expect, his reproof will do me no good; I ſhall ſleight it ſure, putting it to ſome <hi>privy ſhame,</hi> or open reproof. And ſo much touching licencing books, and my want in that particular. And ſo I come to that my ſoul does more deſire to give you ſatisfaction in according to the Scriptures of God; and to unfold your underſtanding. Firſt touching the true ſenſe and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of theſe words <hi>Dependent</hi> and <hi>Independent,</hi> as I find them legible and explained through the Doctrines and Converſations of thoſe men amongſt us, called by that name.</p>
            <p>Briefly now, and as is beſt fitting this place. <q>
                  <hi>Dependent</hi> is a <hi>lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> upon the Lord Chriſt, the onely Beloved of the ſoul; upon His hand for ſtrength; upon His mouth for Direction. It is a ſetting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>up the Lord Chriſt as King; yea, it is the advancing of the Lord Chriſt in all His offices, King, Prophet, and Prieſt, to, in, and over His Church, the ſouls and ſpirits of men. It is a cleaving of the ſoul to Chriſt, a cloſing of the heart with Him, ſaying, Thou <hi>Lord</hi> art my <hi>Righteouſneſſe,</hi> and my <hi>ſtrength;</hi> and my <hi>wiſdome,</hi> and my <hi>glory,</hi> and my <hi>crown of rejoycing.</hi>
               </q> This is to be Dependant, when our Lord Chriſt, who is All to the ſoul, has all its Dependence. And this is to give the Lord God His due, the glory of all His attributes, ſpecially theſe two, the glory of His power, and of His wiſdome: And to the Lord Chriſt King of Saints, His dues, the glory of all His offices, anointed of the Father King, Prophet, and Prieſt of His
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:123891:4"/> Church. And hence I iſſued my thoughts, and thus concluded, That the people (no matter whether many or few; poore or rich; learned or unlearned, Maſter or Diſciple, that the people) we call <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants</hi> are the moſt Dependent perſons in the world. This is the ſum, I ſhall return to this again. Now to the other word.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Independant;</hi> What is that? Ile tell you what it is in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent of, (they ſay) as good a Logician as is in England, now he is here, Ile name him for honour ſake, Doctor <hi>Adam Steuart,</hi> adding onely this, the Lord adde to His Logick, that <hi>one thing neceſſiry,</hi> which one man cals <hi>Baptized</hi> Reaſon, He and we mean, <hi>ſanctified</hi> by the Word and prayer in the Holy Ghoſt: and then he will be good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; <note place="margin">Pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</note> This man ſaies <hi>(A)</hi> 
               <q>That <hi>Independent</hi> is a proud and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable word, proper to God Almighty:</q> 
               <hi>B</hi> It is granted ſo to be, as He conſters the word, and in vulgar conſtruction alſo, as we ſilly men underſtand it too; that to be <hi>Independent,</hi> is to be as an Iſland cut off from other Land; to live as men turned-in-upon themſelves, regarding themſelves, <hi>bearing fruit to themſelves,</hi> (as <hi>an empty vine)</hi> to <note place="margin">Nemini fructuoſa. Hoſ. 10. 1.</note> do as they liſt, ſpeak as they pleaſe, to hold out and maintain what Doctrines agree beſt with fleſh and blood; and to ſpread them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad before Iſrael, and before the Sun, under the very <hi>look</hi> of the Magiſtrate; What has he to do with them? Be they Jews, or Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles; Turks, or Infidels; Atheiſts or Papiſts; be what they will be, as abominable as they are rendred to be, or as we can conceive them to be, why yet, it is their conſcience ſo to be, and what hath the Magiſtrate to do there, or with them? So Dr. <hi>Adam Steuart forceth</hi> matters againſt theſe men; and <hi>forceth</hi> his conſcience too, I verily think all along.</p>
            <p>I ſhould have been fuller here. But, Reader, if this be true in whole or in part; if theſe men, we call Independents, be ſuch men in judgement and in practiſe, as they are ſuggeſted to be, then let the Civill Magiſtrate do with them, as K. <hi>Hez.</hi> with the <hi>Altars</hi> and <hi>high places,</hi> pluck them down; lay them even with the ground; leave them not while there is any one ſtanding; And as with the brazen Serpent, that King dealt with, grinde their faces, beat them as ſmall as the duſt, and then hold them up to the winde, throw them into the River, as the beſt Chriſtians were dealt with of old, that the enemy might take from them, as he could, all Hope of a better Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, let, I ſay, the Magiſtrate do as much to theſe men, for ſo much King <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zekiah</hi> did to the fore-mentioned Idols; And it is full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>up to the mind and heart of Dr. <hi>A. Steuart,</hi> and ſo it follows in his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:123891:4"/> Logick; and ſo he concludes againſt them ſeven times at leaſt, <hi>That theſe men are as contrary to the true Doctrine, Worſhip, and</hi> Diſcipine, as Altars and Idols were and now are. Ile ſpeake for theſe men, and though they neede not my Apology, yet I thinke my ſelfe charged ſo to doe; I have obſerved their converſations; I have heard their Doctrines almoſt theſe 16 yeares; I have read them, ſpecially of late; with all diligence; theſe, I mean, touching Church-Government: I ſhall ſpeake now in the Language of the three Tribes, as heartily as they did, being verily perſwaded, ſo theſe men would ſpeake to clear themſelves in theſe matters ſo <hi>forced</hi> againſt them. <hi>Joſhua 22. ver. 22. The Lord God of gods, the Lord God of gods, Hee knoweth, and Iſrael be ſhall know, if it be in rebellion, or if in tranſgreſſion againſt the Lord, (ſave us not this day;)</hi> 
               <q>That we have ſpoken or done ought <hi>to turne from following the Lord;</hi> or if to offer to the Lord prayers of our own; or to the people, the Church of God, Doctrines of our own, Ordinances of our own, <hi>let the Lord Himſelfe require it:</hi> And let him, to whoſe hand, the Lord has committed the <hi>ſword,</hi> conſecrate the fame ſword on us, to the cutting of us off from the earth.</q> So theſe ſervants of the Lord can ſay.</p>
            <p>And Reader, be not deceived with vain words, but be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in thy heart, that theſe men ſo ſlandered, doe regard others as they ſtand charged by the word of God to regard them. They ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thy ſoule, and mine more precious then is the whole world, and all the treaſures there, (for theſe may be valued but the ſoule cannot) And knowing <hi>the terrous of the</hi> Lord, they <hi>perſwade men to bee reconciled.</hi> They abominate thoſe in Doctrines and practiſes, al which <hi>turne away from following the Lord.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 13.</note> They know the Command of the Lord is in as full force and vertue now, as ever it was, let <hi>ſuch practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers</hi> (intiſers rather) be <hi>cut off,</hi> that <hi>their mouthes neay be ſtopt.</hi> They ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit not of any Toleration, neither that Jews nor Papiſts be tolerated in a Kingdome any ſurther then as means may be uſed, whereby to enlarge the bounds of their Lord Chriſts Kingdome, To bring them under the <hi>ſubjection of the Goſpel,</hi> ſo far to be tolerated, no farther; not as Jewes and Turkes are tolerated, for gaine of money; or as we tolerated Papiſts here, ſuffered them in the Land, &amp; engaged our ſelves againſt all means for their converſion, that is abominable. But to ſuffer them amongſt us with a pure aime to the gaining of ſoules, and a ſingle eve to Gods Glory, this is tolerable ſure, for it is according to the will of God, that the bounds of his Sonnes King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhould be enlarged, and all meanes uſed whereby to <hi>concince</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:123891:5"/> 
               <hi>the ganeſayers,</hi> To Conquer the Rebellious; to make them obedient both <hi>in word and deede:</hi> And for this great conqueſt over the ſoules and ſpirits of men, the throwing down thoſe <hi>Reaſonings,</hi> the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds there, for this mighty worke, the ſword of the Spirit, the word <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> of God is appointed and conſecrated for that very end by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ſo I ſay; nay, ſo the Lord God ſayes, and ſo ſay the <hi>Indepeaedents</hi> from his mouth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> But it is a proud and an abominable name, proper to God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, ſayes the Doctor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>B.</hi> Proper to him indeede, to him alone, and yet not improperly given to a peculiar people, a <hi>Royall Prieſthood</hi> to be <hi>Independant</hi> upon man, <hi>Dependant</hi> upon the Lord Chriſt, leaning upon that beloved; the onely ſtay and ſtaffe of His People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The very name Independent renders them odious to all men, It overthrows all kinde of government, takes away the rights and priviledges of Aſſemblies, Councels, Sinods, takes from them their dues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>B.</hi> Noe, Theſe men give to men their dues. all and every whit to the leaſt ſcruple. They will raiſe men up to their proportioned heighth, no highter, for that were to doe unto men the greateſt inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that could be imagined; to raiſe up men above the <hi>Starres of God,</hi> is to throw them downe even to the <hi>ſides of the pit.</hi> To make men Lords over the conſciences of men, is to render them abominable to God and good men; and as <hi>Antichriſtians</hi> every whit, as are Arch-Biſhops and Biſhops. They will give unto men the power which God allows them, They will raiſe-men-up to their proper pegg, as high as befitteth the higheſt creatures upon earth, yet ſo as exalting ever more the <hi>high God</hi> their Creator, and the Lord Chriſt <hi>King of Saints.</hi> Theſe men will <hi>appeale</hi> alſo to men in point of Counſell and power both, ſo far as they will conſult with the Scriptures of God, with their <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Iudge</hi> there, both one: So Dependant they are even upon men. Independent in this ſence only, not bottoming themſelves, or their faith upon men: for that were to doe as a foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh builder who built his houſe upon the ſands: nor ſtating their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations touching Church Government after the mindes and pleaſures of men, not as they ſay, and would have it; but as the Scriptures of God will have it, where they have their Rule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> But who ſhall be judge of that rule?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>B.</hi> A ſtrange Queſtion; The Spirit of God there, for as was ſaid, He is the <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Judge</hi> both. And this ſeemes to come up cloſe to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:123891:5"/> the good word of God which we read; <hi>And the reamnant of Iacob ſhall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Micah. 5. 7.</note> 
               <hi>be in the midſt of many people as a dew from the Lord, as the ſhowethe rs upon the graſſe, that tarrieth not for man, nor wayteth for the ſonnes of men.</hi> And thus, Sir, I have given you as plain and briefe * a Commentary on theſe <note place="margin">It is more enlarged in my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to ſix Queſtions (24 will ſhrinke up 10 ſo few) which wayt a licence, but have loſt, nothing by wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ting ſo long.</note> two words, <hi>Dependent</hi> and <hi>Independent</hi> as poſſibly I could. And now if you will reckon me among the <hi>Independents,</hi> I ſhall account it no wrong, I ſhall not put it to the head of injuries. And (2) then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count me in the number of ſuch evill doers, and <hi>Troublers;</hi> that I doe helpe with them, to open a floud-gate, &amp;c. If or ſo they are ſuggeſted, to doe. Truly, (Sir) I muſt account this an honour: For fo they perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted (A leſſer matter then this, in fight, is regiſtred a perſecution, when it was as this is, againſt the beloved childe and faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of the Lord, who walked after the Spirit, ſo they that were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſh perſecuted) the firſt <hi>Fathers, Patriarkes, Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> all the Saints and Armies of Martyrs upward to, <hi>as it is at this day.</hi> Therefore as the ſaying is <hi>verbera,</hi> purſue your perſecutions (you doe it I know out of ignorance) <hi>ſedaudi,</hi> beware and conſider what you doe; and now harken while I ſhall endeavour to render you ſatisfied touching theſe two matters, eſpecially the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.</p>
            <p>(1) I am indeede an Independent in judgement, my ſoule go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out with them in that <hi>way;</hi> with them, perſwaded in my ſoule, that their ayme is wholy to the ſetting up the Lord Chriſt, Him in all His Offices, in and over the Church, in the ſoules, and ſpirits of men. And that their eye is ſingle in all this, looking ſtrait-on to the Glory of the high God, and ſalvation of ſoules.</p>
            <p>(2) And that <hi>Independencie</hi> is no more, nor any more intended by it, then purely to take themſelves and others off from their own bottomes, that all might be ſet upon the <hi>Foundation</hi> indeede, the Rock of <hi>Ages,</hi> the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(3) And all this ſo as they give the Rulers of the people, their ſtanding; firme, faſt, and unſhaken, like the <hi>perpetuall hills and everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting mountains,</hi> A faſt-ſtanding, I ſay, while the world ſtands in their full power, force, and vertue; for no <hi>Law</hi> or <hi>Ordinance</hi> have they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this the Rulers ſtanding, being the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of GOD ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed and decreed by Himſelfe.</p>
            <p>(4) For that way of worſhip, and Church-government my judgement ſtands for, I am verily perſwaded it is the way of the New <hi>Teſtament; new</hi> if you will, but no more <hi>Novell</hi> than is that <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:123891:6"/>
            <p>(5) For their walking in that way, it is in ſuch order, with ſuch agreement, complying of Spirits, ſuch an eying and fixing upon the rule, what is decent and expedient, what ſerveth moſt aptly, tends moſt compendiouſly to promote the <hi>edification,</hi> the building-up of the Temple of Chriſt; That I have this perſwaſion, that they who have obſerved the way, and the brethrens walking in it, will ſpeake of it in the Apoſtles words; <hi>Joying and beholding your order and your ſtedfaſtneſſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Col. 2. 5.</note> 
               <hi>of your faith in Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly, Sir, my judgement is, for that <hi>way</hi> of Government, Gods way, I am verily perſwaded; As, for mans way, Maſter or Diſcipline my judgement is not for it, further then as they walke in the way with a <hi>right foote;</hi> nor for their gathering of Churches further then as they doe it by the call of the word, ſo as man may not bee ſaid to doe it, but God rather by the <hi>call</hi> of His Spirit and word of His truth. Nor is my Judgement for mens <hi>ſcatternings</hi> in the way, though there will be ſcatterings there; Let thoſe ſcatterers be marked and rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>ſharpely,</hi> for they ſhould walke exactly; All about them in ſight, cloathes, geſture; And all from without them in the eyes and eares of men, their words and actions, ſhould be <hi>vocall,</hi> all, as we ſay, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king forth <hi>holineſſe</hi> to the Lord; grace and edification to the hearers and beholders. But yet if men walke as men <hi>ſcattering</hi> their wayes, yet theſe their <hi>ſcatterings</hi> muſt not caſt a reproach upon the holineſſe of Gods way, after which my ſoule goeth forth. And yet my foote, my ſtanding I mean, is in the other way, whereof my thoughts have beene ever honourable as becommeth; So of my <hi>Miniſter</hi> alſo, one that feareth God above many; ſet over me in that way of Church Government, I reverence him heartily: I approve his care, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his aymes and ends to be <hi>holy juſt</hi> and <hi>good; The glory of God, The eternall good of ſoules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> What, and yet your judgement for the other way? ſurely looke what way the judgement goes, your foote ſhould goe; where your heart can fixe, there your ſtanding ſhould be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>B.</hi> Truly it may be a truth in what you ſay, but I am not reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſo: For, firſt, I ſtand not alone but together with a whole houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold with me, in ſeverall relations to all theſe, as a Husband, a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a Maſter; And, truly, I dare not attribute ſo much to my judgement, or to a way, I think more excellent, as to fit looſe from my Reverend Paſtor: or remove my ſelfe and mine (for I cannot allow of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ragling family, the head going one way, and the other part another way, I ſaid my ſelfe and mine) from under his care
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:123891:6"/> and charge, whom, I know the Lord has ſet to look, and ſee-over me and mine.</p>
            <p>2 I ſtand ſtill in my ſpirit, reſolved there, that, ſeeing by a good providence, two parties have ſo eagerly claſhed together, and ſo charged themſelves, and before their God, to find out the way of God, both of them I hope, with pure aymes, and a ſingle eye, (I am at an agreement with my thoughts) That the good Lord will beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth and make plain his own way; ſo as, what lay too looſe and ſcattering in the one <hi>way,</hi> ſhall be gathered-up and ſtrengthened: and what might be too high, and rough in the other way, may be taken down and made more levell, ſmooth and ſtrait for us to walk in; I mean, and I am full of hope ſo it will be, That there will be, by the good hand of God upon His ſervants, notwithſtanding their <hi>charging</hi> and <hi>recharging,</hi> a ſweet compliauce anon, an yeelding and bending each to others way, as neer as can be (keeping neer and cloſe to the Word) and as is becoming Brethren, holding the <hi>unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace:</hi> I ſtand ſtill in my ſpirit and full of hope, touching this matter, The meeting of both theſe wayes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one, the <hi>good</hi> and <hi>Holy way.</hi> Though truly, I cannot conceive where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Independants can yeeld one foot, or one hoof of a foot (for they muſt be daintie if not imperious in Gods matters) except in point of <hi>power;</hi> An high point that, where and in whom it muſt be ſtated: ſtate it where they will, (for I know they will ſtate it as neer as poſſibly they can look, to the mind, and will of their God, in his Scriptures:) But I would not have that, which the Scripture calls the <hi>keyes,</hi> intruſted in our hands, common people. For truly what ever we think we know, yet is it a point of knowledge too high for us, to know how to uſe them. Yet I could ſpeak much more in the commendations of us <hi>Laymen,</hi> then I can for the <hi>Clergie-men:</hi> for when we were at the worſt, we were better then our teachers, not half ſo brutiſh as they; ſound ſome of us, when our Miniſters were rotten moſt of them; ſound in the faith, when our Miniſters were abominably here<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icall, touching the Lords Day, his worſhip and ſervice on that day. The Conſideration whereof, if ſad, and ſerious, and well laid to heart, may be of force ſufficient, to make the beſt Clergy-men in the Land, to walk ſoftly, ſorrowing under the ſence thereof after <hi>a godly ſort:</hi> more of this hereafter. Now this one thing more, I profeſſe heartily I can diſcerne nothing in this way of Church Governmen, which my vain heart (the Lord knows I am as far from judging anothers heart, as I am from knowing my own,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:123891:7"/> yet know that I) can except againſt it, but that it is <hi>the way of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, too high for a fool;</hi> and that is my fooliſh exception. I were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to ſet down that I ſee not; or to conceal that I ſee with all mine eyes, no thing but <hi>Holineſſe</hi> all along <hi>this way,</hi> ſuch as ſtands diametrally croſſe to a mans <hi>own way;</hi> and therefore man ſtands ſo croſſe unto it, I mean my ſelf ſtill, or this <hi>ſelf</hi> where ever it is. It chargeth every man with his Brother, to be <hi>his keeper,</hi> Me, to <hi>wat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h</hi> over him; and him to watch over me. To <hi>bear</hi> each others burden; <hi>ſupply</hi> each others lack, that there be no lack to any member of the Body; An excellent <hi>way</hi> and muſt be taken, elſe the Body may ſwim now, and perhaps fink anon; It may be ſo bowed-down with preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing wants, that, though It lives at preſent, yet may it famiſh in the houſe next day, or ſtarve in the ſtreets next night, if this care be not taken, as ſure enough it is not. But this care is taken, even over the Bodies, That there be no lack to them. The care over the ſoul ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds, as that exceeds the Body. And ſo they ſtand charged in their care each over other: Oh this, and more there is, is an hard burden, this <hi>ſelf</hi> will not bring our ſhoulders to it: And yet we owe, in point of bearing each the others burden, ſo much as this, to our enemies <hi>Ox</hi> or <hi>Aſſe,</hi> even his, <hi>that hateth us;</hi> how much more to the ſoul of our <note place="margin">Exod. 23. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 5.</note> brother? But I ſay, we fly-off from this duty; we ſtand naturally croſſe centered to it, all our way; for indeed there is to my diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nothing, but God in the way, with <hi>whom</hi> the heart would not cloſe; Whereas in the way we call <hi>Praesbyterian</hi> [As it has been or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered; underſtand me ſo, for as it is <hi>ordering,</hi> It will be <hi>Independent</hi> ſure; this being granted That a <hi>ſtrict Presbyterian</hi> is a <hi>True Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent:</hi> And a <hi>Rigid Presbyterian</hi> is as high as was a Lord Biſhop, and but a little below a <hi>Pope,</hi> In that way] there is much of man, to ſay no more, but too much of mans Inſtitution, with which the heart can cloſe but too well. And this confirmeth me, That the way we call <hi>Independent</hi> is the True way of Worſhip: Becauſe it is ſo ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, ſo croſſe to mans way and <hi>will-worſhip,</hi> as they do find it to be, who walk in it with a <hi>right foot;</hi> And this was the very Argument, whereby <hi>Luther</hi> confirmed himſelf, and all his friends touching the proſecution of a great cauſe, the Truth and Proſperity of the ſame; <hi>It is of God,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>and it ſhall proſper:</hi> Why proſper? or how proves he that? for it exalts the <hi>Lord:</hi> and depreſſeth man: It renders God All to His people; and mens devices, how ſpecious ſoever, of ſmall account, or nothing at all. And ſo much, Sir, to reſolve you, which way my judgement goes; and yet why I keep my ſtanding. I deſire
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:123891:7"/> now heartily to give you ſatisfaction in the ſecond place.</p>
            <p>2 Touching that heavy charge againſt the <hi>Independents,</hi> That they open a flood-gate, &amp;c. It is true, I read it here and there, under three and more mens hands; And if to accuſe be enough, theſe 3. men, not to name the fourth, have done enough, To ſtir-up the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Land, to come-out againſt theſe their Brethren, as we ought now, every mothers child, to come-out againſt grievous woulves. Surely as theſe mens <hi>words</hi> are <hi>hard;</hi> ſo are their <hi>Deeds un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly</hi> againſt their Brethren, the <hi>Meſſengers of the Churches,</hi> and <hi>the glory of Chriſt.</hi> They have <hi>ſet them forth</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaies, he and his companions in the Goſpel, were ſet-out, the <hi>laſt,</hi> men expoſed to the moſt open and extremeſt ſhame, and paine both, <hi>as it were appointed to death,</hi> by the teeth of the moſt Ravening Beaſts; the laſt upon the <hi>Theater</hi> to be made a gazing-ſtock there-on to Angels and Men. So it is now, for they have <hi>ſet-forth</hi> their Brethren, the <hi>laſt,</hi> as the moſt <hi>execrable</hi> and <hi>accurſed</hi> perſons, and accordingly to be dealt-with; ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to be caſt-out and more, but Ile ſay no more, but this ſaid before They have ſet them forth <hi>the laſt, as it were appointed to Death:</hi> And the way of <hi>Independency,</hi> they make the people beleeve, It is as a <hi>gulfe,</hi> which receives all-I know not what to call that all, but they ſay, That all the filth or corruption of Manners and Doctrines emptieth it ſelf-in thither, into that <hi>gulfe,</hi> as into a Common-ſhoare. Theſe are <hi>hard</hi> and Devouring words; and if ſo be their Deeds are not <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly,</hi> yet they have done enough by their words to ſtir-up all the Inhabitants of the Land to put-forth a rough-hand againſt them, who have lived at peace by them, and ſpake good things for them, before their God, touching their everlaſting peace. That I may not ſeem to render their words, <hi>harder</hi> then they are, and more <hi>devouring,</hi> we will hear what their tongues ſay in print (1) <hi>D. P. P.</hi> puts down ſix <hi>ſecundary Cauſes</hi> of our Plagues, the continuance of them; And the Independents he ranks them with the firſt of theſe ſix. The other [whom I need not name, being a man of ſuch Renowne, and name, (and for high Deſert I heartily acknowledge) that his name onely has rendered his <hi>ſubitane Apprehenſions,</hi> in deed and truth ſuch, to ſeem good and ſolid Reaſons; and ſo to paſſe through the City, as having Truth and Reaſon in them: when as indeed and Truth, they have neither the one nor the other; but, as <hi>ſubitane Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> uſe to be, the weakeſt and ſleighteſt as ever came from ſo ſolid a man upon ſo weighty a buſineſſe as is Church Government, yet they take with the people] This man of Name, ſeemes to make a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:123891:8"/> queſtion, and reſolved all the world That <hi>Independencie</hi> is <hi>a Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of <hi>Schifmes:</hi> A <hi>floud gate to let in an inundation,</hi> &amp;c. So the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt.</p>
            <p>The third perſon, Doctor <hi>A Steward</hi> renders the Independents as abominable and pernicious both to Church and State, as are Altars and Orgon-pipes; Croſſes, and Crucifixes: Papiſts, and Atheiſts, yea Sodomites in Iſraels Land, as odious and pernicious as are theſe accurſed perſons and Things. There is the charge full-out, as Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous as man can render it, and it renders the Brethren as odious to the world as man can make them. I ſhould tell you here, how they have drawn-up to this concluſion, I mean, from what <hi>premiſes</hi> they have concluded, as we heard; But truly I finde a diverſion in my thoughts, and I muſt follow them, though I digreſſe a little, that ſo I may come to the <hi>viſions of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am verily perſwaded, that theſe ſervants of the Lord, I meane theſe, who, or whereever they are, that walke in the way, <hi>exactly, preciſely,</hi> as they ought to walke, (I have nothing to ſay unto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,) doe ſee theſe <hi>viſions</hi> frequently now adayes, now that they heare ſuch devouring words, and might feare, but thar the feare of God over-rules in their hearts, the hand of violence put-forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, alſo, <hi>ungodly deeds;</hi> Now is the time for God to appear for them, and to ſay, <hi>I am your God:</hi> for ſo has been His manner in all <hi>perilous</hi> times, ſo to appear to and for His ſervants, as the Churches Chronicles doe tell us all along; but lie keepe to the Scriptures of God, and read backward there. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> heard <hi>devouring words,</hi> and felt <hi>ungodly deedes;</hi> his Adverſaries thruſt him iuto the priſon, there he lay-faſt, ſhut up, and in the darke, not a <hi>Cranny</hi> open to let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Light; Then was Gods time to appear. Then expect the viſions of God: And ſo it was; <hi>And behold a great light;</hi> The light of God ſhined-in upon him, and his fellow priſoner; Indeede the Lord reſerves the greateſt <hi>lights</hi> for the darkeſt roomes, <hi>Priſons</hi> and <hi>Dungeons;</hi> The ſtrongeſt <hi>Conſolations</hi> for the weakeſt hearts, when they are fainting; The ſweeteſt, the goodeſt words, The Lord ſpeakes alwayes to His people in their <hi>wilderneſſe.</hi> That hee does; and ſo wee will read on retrograde.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Marke</hi> tells us a notable ſtory, I doe not remember the Chapter, but the matter I remember very well; That the Lord Chriſt had made a man <hi>every whit whole;</hi> Hee threw-out the devil who did trouble the mans Body, I thinke, his ſoule too; for ſhure He dealt with the man, after his manner, like a <hi>Tormemor.</hi> The Lord
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:123891:8"/> hath ſet His poore ſervant free from his Adverſary, that delights in <hi>proud wrath,</hi> And oh how faine would this ſervant, ſo delivered, have kept ſtill with the Lord Chriſt; but his Lord ſuffered not; but bid him goe to his houſe; then to the Synagogue, give glory to God; but doe not ſay what I have done for thee. The mans heart was full, his tongue muſt needes utter it; he exalts and maguifies the Name of the Lord. The Scribes and Phariſes could not endure it, ſo they excommunicated the poore man, they thruſt him out of their Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues. Then was the Lords time, They had caſt him-out, now the Lord receives him-in: He ſayes unto His poore Caſt-out (in effect) have men thruſt out a rough-hand againſh thee? Thou ſhalt bee at no loſſe by that, Ile <hi>take thee by the hand. Have they</hi> caſt thee out of their <hi>Synagogue?</hi> thou ſhalt not be diſmaid at that, but well apaid rather; <hi>Ile receive thee into my Boſome.</hi> To run-back in my thoughts through all the Old Teſtament even to the beginning, then Ile fix my thoughts upon <hi>Jacob;</hi> He ſaw much trouble in his dayes; And Three of his dayes exceeded, and were very <hi>perilous;</hi> But which is moſt remarkeable; Thoſe were the dayes, which his Lord God choſe to appear unto him in. The firſt day, when hee was leaving his Countrey; and his fathers houſe; bidding farewell, to all his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts and contentments there, a deere Father, and an indulgent mother; when he muſt depart from all thoſe, and with a ſad heart doubtleſſe, Then <hi>behold the viſion of God;</hi> then God appears, God in Chriſt, <note n="*" place="margin">Gen 28. <hi>Jacob</hi> ſees, Ladder, heaven reaching down to e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th, and earth rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hing up to heaven, all meeting to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in on Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſt. Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> then <hi>Jacob</hi> ſees <hi>God,</hi> and heares Him ſpeake good and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable words; <hi>I will be with thee,</hi> Jacob; <hi>where thou art</hi> I will be; A Father to thee, and a Mother both, as loving and tender over thee, as ſhee was; Ile be thy <hi>ſtay,</hi> and <hi>ſtaffe, bread ſhall be given thee,</hi> and <hi>thy water ſhall he ſure;</hi> Ile be thy God, <hi>Jacoh,</hi> Ile bee <hi>All:</hi> ſo as thou ſhalt ſay, having Me, thou haſt <hi>enough,</hi> and enough, <hi>God</hi> and <hi>All. Jacobs</hi> ſecond <hi>perilous</hi> day was, when he ſaw <hi>Labans</hi> countenance changed towards Him, <hi>not as before.</hi> If the countenance is changed, the heart is changed ſure; for the heart changeth firſt; and Jacob may expect <hi>ungodly deedes,</hi> doubtleſſe it was a perilous day with him. But then God appeares to <hi>Jacob;</hi> it Was Gods time, and he ſayes, <hi>Ile be with thee,</hi> And ſaying ſo much, He has ſaid All. <hi>Jacobs</hi> third time, that was <hi>perilous</hi> indeede, it exceeded all compariſon, for he was <hi>diſtreſſed</hi> on that day. <hi>Jacob</hi> is returning to His Countrey and he heares His brother <hi>Eſau</hi> is comming to meete him (a poore weake man with <note place="margin">Gen. 32.</note> his <hi>feeble folke)</hi> and <hi>foure-hundred men with him.</hi> Then <hi>Jacob</hi> was <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly afraid and diſtreſſed,</hi> ſayes the Text: And then, on that very Day,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:123891:9"/> the day of <hi>Jacobs trouble,</hi> His Lord appeareth; And not alone; He has His Angels with Him; <hi>Gods Hoſt;</hi> Nor is that all; <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhall have a double guard now, that he is diſtreſſed, Two Hoaſts for <hi>Eſau's</hi> one; And an Infinite ſtrength, above his brothers; his ſtrength is the ſtrength of men; <hi>Jacob</hi> has the ſtrength of Angels; the Hoſt of God; Nay Hoſts of Angels, <hi>Machanajim,</hi> two Hoſts; for then perils were doubled.</p>
            <p>It is the Lords manner ſo to do, Bleſſed be his Name; When the ſound of Danger is lowdeſt in his ſervant eares; and their eyes can behold nothing but troubles, and fears round about; Then expect, ye ſervants of the Lord (ye that wait His Time, and attend His pleaſure) then expect to ſee <hi>viſions,</hi> and great <hi>ſalvations:</hi> the viſions and ſalvations of God: ſo it has been from the beginning of the world; and ſo it will be to the worlds end. And now I return where I break off, to that heavy-charge drawn-up againſt the Brethren. We muſt ſee whence they have concluded, from what premiſes, I mean, That their brethren muſt be <hi>cut aſunder,</hi> ſo one concludes; <hi>enſe recidendum:</hi> That they muſt be thruſt-out of the Kingdome, as the moſt abominable, and the moſt accurſed things ought to be; ſo the Doctor concludes: from their own <hi>premiſes</hi> all along, which their own hearts ſuggeſted. But without their leaves, we will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine how their concluſion follows, from my <hi>premiſes,</hi> which I have taken from the Scriptures of God. And ſo I will recall the premiſes, and then the charge, theſe 3 men have drawn-up from the premiſes, which are ſummarily theſe. The ſervants of the Lord do Advance their Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as ſole Lord over His Church; They depend upon Him; He is their Righteouſneſſe, their Strength, their Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor in whom they glory. There is their great Dependance, Thereon they <hi>Reſt,</hi> and are <hi>ſtill;</hi> Be men mad with rage; and the earth never ſo unquiet, they are a <hi>quiet habitation</hi> ſtill; for They know whom they have Truſted: Where their great Dependance is, for all Church and State matters, even upon the Lord God Almighty. Dependent they are too upon men, though they put no great truſt there: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>ſtay</hi> nor <hi>ſtaffe,</hi> God knows, yet dependent upon man, for his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and counſell: And accountable for their actions unto men al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, who ſhall, in the name of Chriſt, require an account of them, or of their <hi>repentance,</hi> and <hi>faith towards God.</hi> They will Appeal to men alſo, (that is the great queſtion) ſo be they will Appeal to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (thereunto is their great Appeal) to the Rule and Judge there. So Dependent theſe men are, whom we call (I would we had a fitter
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:123891:9"/> name, ſith it is ſo ill underſtood, and conſtrued: but ſure we have not a fitter name then) <hi>Independant,</hi> for herein they are content and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire rather to be accounted, and called by that name, becauſe they have concluded from their Lords own mouth, and from the practiſe of His Diſciples in the beſt times purely primative, That every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Congregation hath from Chriſt abſolute power, to exerciſe of and in it ſelfe, every Ordinance of God. No <hi>Dependencie</hi> in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or direction in worſhip, from any other than from Chriſt their Lord and Law-giver, made unto His Church their <hi>wiſdome,</hi> their <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> their Juſtification, and their Glory: (Sir) There are the premiſes, Now marke what theſe three men infer, how they draw-up rheir charge from hence. (1) <hi>Ergo,</hi> Theſe Independents are the prime and chiefe cauſes of our plagues and miſeries, ſayes the firſt ſcribe. (2) <hi>Ergo,</hi> Theſe Independents, are the <hi>Seminary</hi> of, &amp;c. and open a floud-gate to all &amp;c. ſaith the Lawyer this once, and I thinke never but this once, cleane beſides the caſe, doubtleſſe God has forgiven him, ſo have his good brethren too, (3) <hi>Ergo,</hi> Thoſe Independents are as abominable, as were Altars, High-places, the Brazen ſerpent, when made an Idol; ſo abominable are theſe men, and to be dealt with by the Rulers hands, as thoſe <hi>Dunghill gods</hi> were dealt withall, when they were throwne-out as an abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and accurſed things; ſo theſe men ſhould be dealt withall, ſayes the Doctor, and ſo concludes. And yet has ſet downe no <hi>premiſes</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the Word of God, whence he concludes ſo, though by his concluſion he has rendred the brethren the moſt odious men and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable, that are in the world, the cauſes of all the miſeries and diſtractions here. Well, let him go on: ſo will I; and by the grace of Almighty God, I will conteſt againſt this <hi>concluſion</hi> with all the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er God will be pleaſed to vouchſafe unto me: And though I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude nothing, yet I ſhall make ſuch <hi>inqairies</hi> into our miſeries, the cauſes thereof, as that theſe <hi>inquiries</hi> onely ſhall ſerve to make a full diſcovery to all the world, touching thoſe matters; and with the ſame labour I ſhall render the Independents and the <hi>way</hi> of worſhip (I have not called it their way or mans way,) as white from thoſe blacks caſt upon them, and the <hi>way,</hi> as is the cloath that hath gone through ſeven la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers; I ſhall have free leave for this ſure, a licence I meane to <hi>enquire</hi> what may be the cauſe of our woes, and ſighes, That every one may put it to queſtion in his own heart; ſet-up the <hi>Inquiſition court</hi> there, and ſo reſolve the Queſtion. But this is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject matter of the <hi>Third Section.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:123891:10"/>
            <p>Here Sir I have given forth the <hi>premiſes,</hi> touching the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents and their Doctrines, as the good word of God gives-them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth to me; and I have ſet down the <hi>Concluſion,</hi> which three men, one after another, as if all had one and the ſame Spirit, have drawn from <hi>premiſes</hi> of their own, deducible neither from <hi>Scripture,</hi> nor from <hi>Reaſon.</hi> no, nor from <hi>ſenſe</hi> neither, unleſſe their own, and that darkened with <hi>prejudice</hi> all along. Surely the man, that has ſo much <hi>Logick,</hi> ſhould not have ſo done, (I ſuppoſe the other two, have as my ſelfe, and other men have, very little, or none, at all in compariſon with him,) But he ſhould not have ſo <hi>concluded</hi> againſt his brethren, That they are as <hi>plagues</hi> and <hi>peſts,</hi> in Judah Land, even as were <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, High-places,</hi> the vileſt Idols there; And yet has ſet downe no <hi>premiſes,</hi> and ſo forth, as aforeſaid. It is replyed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> That the two brethren plead for a <hi>Toleration;</hi> And that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding carries more danger in it to Church and State, than does the pleading for the Service-Booke, Arch-Biſhops, and Biſhops, Altars, and Organs, Croſſes and Crucifixes, that theſe may ſtand in their full force power and vertue. And from hence the Doctor has ſo concluded, againſt his Brethren, for the caſting-of them all forth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>B.</hi> I Anſwer and grant, That the two Brethren doe plead for a <hi>Toleration,</hi> not of all Religions ſure, no, nor of any, which <hi>withdraws</hi> from God; ſurely no ſober man can plead for ſuch a Religion. They plead for a <hi>Toleration</hi> of that Religion or <hi>way</hi> of worſhip, which they are perſwaded in their ſoule, drawes-neereſt to God; And for <hi>Toleration</hi> of theſe men amongſt us, who have ever lived peaceably with us, have ſpoken good things for us before the Throne of God, whoſe Doctrines have come-up fully to the good word of God, and their converſation alſo as becommeth the Goſpel. Now God forbid, that any rough-hand ſhould be put-forth againſt theſe men, Yea, God forgive our <hi>hard words</hi> and <hi>unchriſtian thoughts</hi> that way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> But ſurely, many, whom we call, and they call themſelves, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent,</hi> do think themſelves <hi>exempt from all Laws,</hi> except that law, which <hi>rules in their members:</hi> And think, as the <hi>Nimrods</hi> and <hi>Giants</hi> of the world do think, themſelves accountable for their Actions to none but God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>B.</hi> It were well, if they could bethink themſelves ſeriouſly, That they are accountable to God: but ſo they do not think; But this I know, That many walk <hi>diſorderly,</hi> looſe from their God; the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; and way of His worſhip. But if there be any, who underſtand <hi>Independency</hi> ſo, let them be as odious, and abominable in mans
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:123891:10"/> eye, as the Giants and Nimrods of the world, (mightie hunters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord) are in Gods eye: and let all men come out againſt them, as they ſhould do againſt ſuch mighty oppreſſors; To thruſt them out of the Land. Now let us hear alſo what is commonly ſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That more have fallen off from that way, we call <hi>Independent,</hi> walking their own way, following their own fancies, than from the other way of Church Government. We know not how many have gone-out from us, unto them, been received there, and then have turned away from them again, unto abominable wayes of errors, not to be remembred here. I anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>B.</hi> This may be, and yet the way good and Holy; yea an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment all this, of the goodneſſe and Holineſſe of the way, becauſe ſo many have turned to it, and then quickly away from it. <hi>They went<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out from us, but they were not of us,</hi> ſaies the Apoſtle: And lightly come, lightly gone, ſaies the Proverbe. Theſe entred upon the way with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out due conſideration, upon very light motions; before they weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and pondered their own way, or the way they were entring up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And ſo they are like a ſhip without balas; or as a cloud with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out rain, carried about, &amp;c. Here now, if my advice were worth acceptance, it ſhould be this, to the Maſters of the Aſſemblies; That they would be as daintie in their choice of Members, as <hi>Paul</hi> would have <hi>Timothy</hi> to be in <hi>laying on his hand,</hi> which we call <hi>ordination.</hi> Let it appear, that the <hi>Word</hi> and Spirit gathers members into a Church fellowſhip, and not the call of men: Which will appear, if enquiry be made firſt, whether they have <hi>counted their coſt.</hi> That is a great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry. And whether <hi>their fellowſhip is with the Father and the Son;</hi> and are reſolved to maintain the ſame fellowſhip in that Church-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, they are now entring upon, taking cure and charge one over another, as before ſaid, ſuch as is comely for a communion of Saints? If they can in ſincerity and truth of heart make clear an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers thereunto, that they have no low Aymes; nor baſe <hi>ends</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them to come-over to the vvay: but onely the glory of God, and their more comfortable vvalking ſtill ſearching the Scripture: and vvalking humbly vvith their God: Surely if ſo, there will be be no fear of <hi>falling</hi>-off; but fully aſſured vve may be they vvill vvalk-on ſtrait forward, and hold-on to the end. They are the light, inconſiderate, unſavourie, unballaſed Chriſtians, ſuch as never count their coſt, that are the ſickle men; vvho vvould ſeeme to be ſome bodies vvhen indeed they are <hi>Nothings::</hi> and yet vvould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>Independent men,</hi> taken off from themſelves, and the vvorld,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:123891:11"/> and from every bottome there; <hi>founded</hi> and rooted in Chriſt, vvholly Dependent upon Him, the <hi>Rock of Ages:</hi> And yet vvalk as vvithout God in the preſent World; as they have the men of the World for an example, quite looſe from God and good-men. Oh! this is Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable; and vvill be bitterneſſe at the laſt. To ſhut-up this; They that are received into Church Communion ſhould be men fearing God, and hating covetouſneſſe, who walk not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit: Men, that can hear, and read, and ſing, and pray, and all in the Spirit: Men that walk with God, filled with the Holy Ghoſt: And theſe will ſerve to make Church officers too. It vvill be ſaid again.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> But vvhy do I make ſo large exceptions againſt the Doctors book? I vvas not provoked.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>B.</hi> Not provoked! Indeed I vvas, and ſo I think is every good man; To ſee ſuch a—I cannot tell what to call it, <hi>Charge</hi> is too ſoft a vvord, drawn-up againſt the Brethren, upon the <hi>front</hi> of his book, and in the face of the World. Surely, if I had ſeen ſuch—an <hi>Indictment</hi> againſt the Presbyterians, I ſhould have ſaid as much againſt it and as heartily. And I perſwade my ſelf, they do vviſh, That the Doctors book, and ſuch like, had never ſeen the Sun: or, coming abroad, had been dealt with, as their Authors would have their brethren done unto, <hi>thrown into the fire to be purged there.</hi> And truly if my book be ſo accounted of by any ſober Chriſtian, as a <hi>troubler</hi> of the Churches peace, let it go with its fellows, ſuch <hi>trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers,</hi> and let me be thruſt-out after it. But the Dr. Himſelf does not account me a troubler, a flatterer he ſaies I am. I muſt reply to this firſt.</p>
            <p>If I would flatter, and had skill that way, as truly I have none, but if I had, I would not flatter the Brethren, we call <hi>Independents;</hi> men <hi>ſet forth</hi> the <hi>laſt,</hi> as aforeſaid; I would not flatter them; In the eye of the world, I ſay of the world, I am better than they, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter accounted of then they. But yet we will hear how the Dr. char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth all thoſe, that ſpeak for the Independents or the way of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, thus he ſaies, or to this purpoſe; That the men, who <hi>treat</hi> 
               <q>on their ſide, do beſpeak them, and the people with high ſtrains of Rhetorique and large <hi>laudatives</hi> concerning them:</q> And for his part, he has been a little too free that way, and he craves pardon, Let him have it, for his tongue in print may aſſure us, and all the world, that, if he hath given his Brethren their dues, which he ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth to every man, <hi>ſweet</hi> and <hi>fair language,</hi> he will retract now, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:123891:11"/> do ſo no more, But to quit my ſelf of that my ſoul abhors, baſe flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, giving that to men, which I know they deſerve not, This I will ſay, and not crave pardon for my expreſſion, The Lord God of gods, the Lord God of gods, He knows, That my heart and ſoul has gone-out with my words all along. I have not ſtrained my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in any word I have ſpoken touching our Brethren, and their <hi>way;</hi> It is a beautifull way in my eye, and they have walked with a <hi>right-foot</hi> in that way, ſor ought I can diſcern, or can ken to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. One or more of that ſide or way, may have ſpoken impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly enough, as the Dr. argueth their words, he heard from them in the pulpit. Very likely all that. Alas! Men may walk as men; And it is far from me to commend <hi>mans way:</hi> It is <hi>Gods way</hi> I contend for; man may ſpeak alſo (it is not proper to ſay, he may, but he does) not alwayes as the <hi>oracle of God.</hi> He is a perfect man, ſaith S. <hi>James,</hi> and I beleeve He knew none ſuch in the world, that trips not in his tongue, and foot alſo, who was not an <hi>offender in a word,</hi> yes, and in deed too.</p>
            <p>The Nations are but as a drop of the bucket, and the Iſles as the ſmall duſt of the ballance, in compariſon with the great God; How ſmall and light a thinſt then is hee, we call man? Surely ſurely when we way him, we muſt give him his full allowance, for he is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny graines too light: And yet I muſt not call him <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> a foole, a <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 22. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Vacuus in mis.</hi>
               </note> light and empty fellow; If I call my brother ſo, I am in <hi>danger of a Councel;</hi> the Synod may talke with me for it. and it is fit they ſhould, I abominate jeering or ſcoffing, or any lightnes at all; If any for the Independent way are faulty therein, they are cleane out of the way of God, and good men; and far from the end they ſeeme to propoſe, the perſwading with, and reducing their brother into the way of holineſſe. And hee who is bitter, is far-out too. And now I feele my ſelfe plucked by the eare. I have heard it argued againſt me more than once, <hi>That I blame Mr. Ed:</hi> bitter language, when mine is more <hi>bitter.</hi> Is it ſo? let me be blamed for that, and I aske him pardon too. But I proteſt now before the <hi>Lord and his</hi> people, That though I have beene accuſed, yet I was never ſhown the words, which might argue this bitterneſſe charged upon my Spirit; If ſuch they are in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny corner of my booke, which can bear ſuch a conſtruction, they ſlipt from me before I was aware, yet I will own them, if there they be, as my own, the fruit of my own Spirit, and reprove my ſelfe and my words more than another neede to doe; yea, and abominate ſuch
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:123891:12"/> words alſo, all and every one, which have ſuch an <hi>Aſpect</hi> upon my brother, but I ſay again, and I ſay truly, I have not yet found any ſuch word in my booke: but I can too eaſily over-looke my own words or actions, as an unfit Judge in ſuch matters. Yet let me tell you what I ought to doe, and what I would doe, ſo I ſhall the better argue againſt my three brethren hereaſter. That if I were to ſpeake to Turker or Jewes; Atheiſts or Papiſts; the moſt untoward and rougheſt men in the world, yet I would render my words as <hi>ſmooth as oyle,</hi> and <hi>as ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ft as Butter,</hi> that the men I ſpeake unto might know in their hearts, and be perſwaded in their ſoules, that I have no war againſt them in my heart; no, but that I keowing the terrour of the Lord, doe ſeeke their peace, their ſoules peace; that I would perfwade with them for their everlaſting good: And by this means J would hope to make my words keene in the hearts of our Lords, and His Chriſts chiefeſt enemies; and if J had a word from the Lord, by the grace of God, that J would fet-on with all my might, but with the ſpirit of meekneſſe. We have an excellent patterne for this; To ſpeak ſo to my Brother, as that my Brother may perceive that I would do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him good with all my Heart and all my ſoule: For ſo the high God, the great Lord of heaven and earth, Even ſo he ſpeaketh to his poore ſervants; I will doe you good (ſayes He) with My <hi>whole heart and My wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le ſoule.</hi> Oh the goodneſſe of God! His kindeneſſe to his creatures, ſo he treates with men! O! bleſſed be His name. Have theſe three ſervauts of the Lord imitated their Maſter? I ſhould not put it to Queſtion, for paſt all Queſtion they have done cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. What the good King ſaid in the Anguiſh of his Spirit, the ſame theſe men have ſaid in the tartneſſe frowardneſſe, eagerneſſe <note place="margin">Iſa 38.</note> of their own <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>bitterneſſe bitterneſſe,</hi> bitterneſſe in their tongues, and that could not be but when there is more in the heart, aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of bitterneſſe there; whence it is that their pens have beene dipped in vinigar and ſteeped as in gall: <hi>bitterneſſe, bitterneſſe,</hi> as if they intended not, as ſure they did not, to informe their brethren, and recall them from error, if in any they are, but to inbitter their ſpirits, and give them a bill from their hands, in full aſſurance, that they will endeavour, without the grace of God, to diſcover and lay open their brethrens nakedneſſe to all the world, with <hi>their whole heart, and with their whole ſoule.</hi> Is this to imitate the Lord God Father of mercies, God of, all Conſolations? To put this out of queſtion ile ſay this more, that there is not a man, on this ſide our narrow ſeas,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:123891:12"/> whoſe hand has appeared for the Presbyterian way of Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, not one man (except that excellent man Mr. <hi>Herle,</hi> it were a notable indignity offered unto him, not to except him) that has not bent the ſame hand againſt his brethren, making his words ſharp as arrows ſhot-out againſt their very faces; I had almoſt ſaid, and hearts too, ſo giving all the vvorld to knovv (I ſpeak my jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie at leaſt) that their <hi>paſſions</hi> are ſtrong, but their cauſe is weak. But this I know; That we have not ſo learnt the Lord Chriſt; This is not after our Lords manner, nor after the Cuſtomes of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of God. I have ſaid vvhat I have to ſay touching this filthy and putred matter, vvhich like a box of the vileſt and impureſt oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is ſuffered to run abroad through Church and State to fill the houſe there vvith its filthy ſavour. Ile cloſe this box vvith this ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, it may be of uſe to ſtop the mouth againſt <hi>devouring words;</hi> Such kind of vvritings or Reaſonings, ſavouring ſo ſtrong of fleſh and blood, vvill never do the world good, to make them knovv they lie in evill; Nor the cauſe good, mightie Adverſaries thereunto; nor the Church good, To make them knovv their ſins, and confeſſe their errors; never do the State or Church good this vvay, vvhile the world ſtands, unleſſe by <hi>accident,</hi> as the <hi>Logicians</hi> ſay (i e) by the wiſe diſpoſing, and gracious ordering of an Almighty hand: ſo they ſhall do all good; But not <hi>per ſe,</hi> as vve ſay, not by their own naturall working, vvhile the world ſtands. And when the vvorld muſt fall to peeces, and the <hi>Things</hi> there crumbled all to <hi>nothings;</hi> and the perſons there muſt render an account of all they have ſaid, and done, then theſe kind of writings will be <hi>bitterneſſe, bitterneſſe.</hi> Their Authors ſhall taſte, if they repent not, of their own Gall, and worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, there, vvhich they themſelves have put-in: and it ſhall be their drink, and portion for ever. Then the tongue, which was ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on fire of hell, and repented not, ſhall have Hell and fire long enough, as long as <hi>eternitie</hi> is long, for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>It is a ſad <hi>period,</hi> I will not put <hi>Amen</hi> to it: my ſoule deprecates, praies againſt this end. But Ile <hi>pray in prayer,</hi> if I could in prayer I would pray; Lord give the brethren all foure, (I might ſay foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore, here, and there, and every where, give them <hi>Lord,</hi> repentance for all their hard words and ungodly deedes againſt the brethren, the faithfull ſervants of the Lord, <hi>Amen:</hi> make them Lord as all the Tribes ſhall be, <hi>all one,</hi> as <hi>one ſtick in Thy hand,</hi> to beate away the doggs and ſwine: All as one aſſembly of Saints, built-up as a <hi>Ciey that is</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:123891:13"/> 
               <hi>compacted together;</hi> or as a houſe founded upon the <hi>Rock of Ages,</hi> faſt and ſure for ever, notwithſtanding, the fierce windes, great rains, and water-flouds; for this Rock is our Rock: <hi>He will be our guide, even unto the death.</hi> 1 Pet. 3. 8, 9. <hi>Finally be ye all of one minde, having compaſſion one of another, be as brethren, be pitifull be cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous: Not rendring, evill for evill, or rayling for rayling: but contrarywiſe bleſſing, knowing that ye are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto called, that you ſhould inherit a bleſſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
